Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project, 593058
  - Walters, [Unknown Man], Undated; 593522 (Box 99, Reel 993a, Box 76, Reel 993b)
    Mr. Walters was born in Jamaica in 1895. His father was a stonemason and his mother worked as a housekeeper for a doctor in Albany, New York. He and his parents immigrated to the United States (US) when he was 19 years old. He lived in the Hell's Kitchen neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and attended an unspecified vocational school for carpentry. He worked in the construction industry as a carpenter and mechanic and joined an unspecified construction workers' union in New York City.
    The interview with Mr. Walters was conducted by Victor Scheluchin at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York on April 18, 1973. The first name of the narrator is unknown. This interview covers Mr. Walters' childhood in Jamaica; his immigration to the United States (US) when he was 19 years old; and his life and work in the construction industry in New York, New York. Walters begins by describing the reason his family immigrated to the US, noting that his family moved primarily due to economic conditions. He explains that many of his relatives had already immigrated to the US and some of his immediate family and distant relatives followed his family after their immigration. He notes that the family made sure to help any new members adjust to life in the US. He recalls attending an unspecified vocational school at which he learned carpentry, and working in the construction industry as a carpenter and mechanic. He recalls working on the George Washington Bridge, Madison Square Garden, The Daily News Building, the subway in Queens, and schools near the City College of New York. He joined an unspecified construction workers' union in New York City, which he remembers specifically for its assistance in reducing working hours. Walters lived in the Hell's Kitchen neighborhood of Manhattan and noticed that, while he felt safe in his neighborhood, there was a divide between the white and black populations. He emphasizes the role of the sanitation workers in New York City, explaining that he believes that they are more important than the police because they keep the city clean. He notes that while gangsters have consistently been a problem in New York City, narcotics have made the generation coming of age at the time of the interview more violent and destructive than their predecessors. Other topics include his family's religion; a comparison of the relevance of the church in the past and at the time of the interview; the importance of a construction worker's tools; his experience during the Prohibition era; racial and ethnic segregation and discrimination in New York City neighborhoods; his leisure time in a book club; and a comparison of New York City in the past and at the time of the interview.
    See also: Council Workshop for Senior Citizens II; and Interview Compilation for Radio Broadcast.
    Construction workers -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews
  - Wanderling, Angelina, Undated; 344219 (Box 69, Reel 211a - 211d, Box 1, Folder 89)
    Angelina Wanderling was born in 1902 in New York, New York. She lived in the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan. Her parents were born in Salerno, Italy and immigrated to the United States in the late 19th century. Her father worked in sanitation. Wanderling left school after completing the eighth grade and started working in the garment industry, first as a floor girl and then as a machine operator. She was a member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) Local 89. She married and had two children. Her husband was a house painter. At the time of the interview, she volunteered as a friendly visitor for the ILGWU.
    This interview was conducted by Santa Cigliano-Laudiero. The date and location of the interview are unknown. The interview covers Angelina Wanderling's working life, her union activity, and her family. Wanderling discusses her early work experiences in garment factories, including not enjoying section work because of the repetition, and looking for better jobs. She discusses her attempts at organizing factories in which she worked and the opposition she met from immigrant workers who were afraid to lose their jobs. She describes herself as aggressive and dissatisfied with the poor working conditions in the factories, but understanding the hesitation of the other workers. She recounts a strike in 1932 and 1933 led by the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) in which she convinced her co-workers to participate; one factory where workers had not joined the strike and her decision to disconnect the factory's electricity; and the benefits the ILGWU gained for them after the strike. She discusses her work as the chairlady in the factory, in particular convincing management that the work involved more than sewing and that workers' examination of the garments and adaption to new styles should be included in their salary. She discusses her decision to leave and return to the workforce at different times, the types of work she performed, and the salaries she received.
    Wanderling discusses her family; her parents' immigration to the United States; the love her father showed her and her siblings; her mother's work raising 13 children; and her own children and grandchildren. She discusses childbirth, comparing her experience to her mother's and describing why women feared giving birth in a hospital in the late 19th and early 20th centuries. Other topics include her love of movies; her education; her desire to know what sort of women would wear the clothes on which she worked; and the types of apartments in which she lived with her husband and children.
    Childbirth |z New York (State) |z New York.; Women labor leaders -- New York (State) -- New York
  - Ward, Katherine, 1974 April 24; 592024
    Katherine Ward was born in 1867 in County Sligo, Ireland. She immigrated to the United States (US) through Castle Garden, New York and lived with relatives in Morrisville, Pennsylvania. She lived with an aunt in New Jersey for two years before moving to New Haven, Connecticut with another aunt. In New Haven, Ward was employed making boxes at Sargent and Company. She married in 1889 and had two daughters and one son. During World War I, Ward and her family moved to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania for her husband's work as a surveyor. Her husband died in 1933; one of their daughters died in 1967; and their son died in 1972.
    This interview was conducted by John Davenport at Katherine Ward's home on April 24, 1974 by an unknown interviewer. Ward's daughter, Katherine, assists her during part of the interview. Main topics include Ward's life in Ireland, her immigration to the United States (US), her employment, and her marriage and family. Ward discusses her family in Ireland, including her mother's birth on Coney Island, Ireland; her father's employment as a farmer; her parents' arranged marriage; her nine siblings; and the death of her mother when Ward was nine years old. She recalls studying to be a teacher in Ireland and taking promotion examinations proctored by British academics. She discusses her family's difficulty with protecting their property from destruction and theft by the English.
    Ward discusses her immigration to the US, including sailing from Dublin to Liverpool, England to Castle Garden in Manhattan, New York; being extremely seasick throughout the voyage; and being met in New York by her great-aunt from Morrisville, Pennsylvania. Ward recalls being employed by Sargent and Company in New Haven, Connecticut making boxes; working as an organizer for the Knights of Labor; and being fired from Sargent and Company after management learned she was associating with union workers.
    Ward discusses her husband, including their meeting in New Haven during the Blizzard of 1888; his proposal after she was fired from Sargent and Company; and their wedding in January of 1889. She discusses their children, including their daughters' education at St. Mary's Academy and Albertus Magnus College in New Haven; the fact that their daughters both became teachers; the death of their son in 1972 due to a stroke; and the death of one of her daughters in 1967 from an aneurism.
    Throughout the interview Ward shares anecdotes about family members in Ireland and the US, including her grand-aunt being disowned because she married an Englishman and her father threatening English hunters with a pitchfork after they rode through his cabbage garden.
    See also: Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York, New York and the United States; Leisure; Passage; and Unionization.
  - Weiner, Jean, 1975 March 2, March 28, and April 11; 344220 (Box 69, Reel 212a, Box 70, Reel 212b - 212f, Box 71, Reel 212g, Box 1, Folder 90)
    Jean Weiner was born in a small village in Bessarabia, Russia and was one of four children. Her father was a tailor and immigrated to the United States in the first decade of the 20th century. He worked as a finisher on ladies' coats, suits, and capes. The rest of the family joined him four years later and lived on Clinton Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Weiner worked as a seamstress in ladies' garment and underwear factories. She was a member of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union). She was married.
    This interview was conducted by Louise Mayo on March 2, March 28, and April 11, 1975 at Jean Weiner's daughter's home and other unspecified locations. The interview covers Jean Weiner's childhood in Bessarabia, Russia; her family's life after their immigration to the United States (US); her working life; and her union activity. Weiner describes the daily life of her family in Bessarabia in great detail, including specifics on her father's tailoring business; the food her mother would prepare for the family; how her mother made extra money while her father was in the US; and the importance her father placed on education. She describes the different types of apartments the family rented as they moved into better apartments in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York before being able to afford a private house on Vermont Street in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. She recounts that the family had boarders; that her many relatives would frequently visit; how she enjoyed having so many people in the house; and that family and friends would help each other in times of need or illness. She compares the way the family lived in Russia to their life in the US, describing the variety of meat that was available in the US; the way the family shopped for food and goods, mainly from pushcarts on Rivington Street in the Lower East Side; and the different status levels amongst the working class in both countries, which were determined by a person's profession. She recounts her working life, which began soon after she arrived in the US; how much money she was expected to contribute to the household; the division of labor between men and women; and the fact that there were certain jobs that only men could do.
    While Weiner does not specify to which union she belonged (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union), she describes her union activity in great detail. She recounts the benefits to working in a union shop and a strike in which she participated. She describes in great detail the chairwoman of her local, whom she describes as well-educated, radical, and a Socialist. She discusses deciding to take a vacation from work as she had enough money to do so and spending the summer with her mother and siblings in Huntington, Connecticut; she and her sister flirting with young men in front of a country store near their camp; and meeting her husband through one of these men. Other topics include the family's more secular life in the US; the Jewish street gang, The Little Augies; life in Jewish neighborhoods in New York City; and pride in her ability to work so that her youngest brother and sister were able to graduate high school and attend college.
    Transcript, index, and summary are available for this interview.
    Women labor union members -- New York (State) -- New York
  - Weinstein, Helen Taub, 1974 May 1; 344221 (Box 71, Reel 213a - 213b, Box 1, Folder 91)
    Helen Taub Weinstein was born on July 26, 1897 in Russia. Her family moved outside of Krakow in the Polish region of Austria-Hungary when she was young. She married in 1920 and had three children, one of whom died in World War II.
    This interview was conducted by Suzanne Michel at the Bialystoker Home for the Aged in Manhattan, New York on May 1, 1974. The interviewer and location are unknown. The interview covers Helen Taub Weinstein's childhood in Austria-Hungary; her family's immigration to the United States (US); her family's religious beliefs; her encounters with anti-Semitism in Austria-Hungary and the US; and her personal life. Weinstein describes her childhood outside of Krakow and the resort her parents owned there. She describes Franz Joseph I's lenient attitude towards the Jewish population, in opposition to the majority of the population of Austria-Hungary. She recounts her family's decision to emigrate due to rising anti-Semitism in 1911 or 1912. She discusses the family's resort in Monticello, New York and her work there. She recalls teaching Polish at the school in Monticello and being paid in fruit and vegetables as she did not have a teaching license. She discusses the difference in religious observance between her parents' generation and her own and the anti-Semitism her children faced in school in Queens and Long Island. She describes the loneliness she feels as an older person isolated from her family and the devastation she felt over the death of her oldest son during World War II.
    Catskill Mountains (N.Y.) |v Anecdotes.
  - Williams, Ellen, 1975 October 23, November 12, and December 3; 344222 (Box 71, Reel 214a - 214b, Box 72, Reel 214c - 214f)
    Ellen Williams was born on April 30, 1938 in Darliston, Jamaica. She was one of nine children. Her father was a coachman and a farmer and her mother managed the household. Williams attended school in Jamaica up to the sixth standard in the British education system. She immigrated to the United States on June 17, 1947 and lived with her cousin at 68 West 117th Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She married in 1948 and lived on 120th Street in Harlem. She later moved to Morningside Avenue in the Morningside Heights neighborhood of Manhattan and to the Bronx, where she resided at the time of the interview. She worked as a baby nurse for various families in New York City and as a nurse's aide in the Jewish Home and Hospital for the Aged in the Upper West Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She joined Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in 1963 or 1964. She was a member of the West Indian and American Friendly Society and St. John's Lodge in New York City.
    This interview was conducted by Sasha Silverstein at the offices of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in Manhattan, New York on October 23, November 12, and December 3, 1975. This interview covers Ellen Williams' childhood in Darliston, Jamaica; her immigration to the United States (US); and her life and work as a baby nurse and a nurses' aide in New York, New York. Williams begins by describing her childhood in Jamaica, specifically recalling her father's occupation as a coachman in Kingston; the perception of this job as prestigious due to the wages and uniforms; and his occupation later as a pimento and coffee farmer in Darliston. She recalls that despite the racial segregation in the schools and churches, children were generally friendly with one another. She describes working as a baby nurse for a family in Jamaica, noting that they treated her like family; deferred to her on matters regarding their children; and introduced her to politicians and other friends of theirs. She discusses the differences between life in the city and in the country; the different roles of men and women in both the household and society; the finances of her household; Catholic traditions, including holiday services and the role of godparents; and other secular traditions, particularly birthdays and festivals.
    Williams explains that she immigrated to the US at the behest of her cousin and recalls the sponsorship and monetary requirements for her immigration in June 1947. Her initial impression of New York City was that it was filled with trees and well-dressed people. She explains that while her cousins helped her to acclimate to life in New York, she had difficulty adapting to the winter weather. She describes working as a baby nurse for various families in New York City, recalling that after her marriage in 1948, she only took jobs that did not require her to live with her employers. She describes her work and training as a nurse's aide at the Jewish Home and Hospital for the Aged in the Upper West Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Williams recalls joining Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in 1963 or 1964 and notes that despite her initial skepticism of its benefits, the union gave hospital workers greater job security and wage increases. Other topics include the differences between her work as a baby nurse and nurse's aide; her siblings' education, careers, and families; her husband's occupation and family; her interactions with and impressions of union leaders, particularly Doris Turner and Leon Davis; her involvement in the West Indian and American Friendly Society and St. John's Lodge; and her visits to Jamaica to see her family.
    Jamaicans |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
- Preservation Masters
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 102)
    Cassettes 1 - 44B
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 103)
    Cassettes 45 - 76
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 104)
    Cassettes 76A - 117
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 105)
    Cassettes 119 - 152
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 106)
    Cassettes 154 - 180B
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 107)
    Cassettes 181 - 204
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 108)
    Cassettes 205 - 222A
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 109)
    Cassettes 222B - 239
  - Preservation Masters, 1972-1976, undated (Box 110)
    Cassettes 240 - 257